Good morning. Today's דף daf is דף ג' daf gimmel מנחות Menachos
and we are dealing with the position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
We're dealing with whole issue of שלא לשמה, shlo lishmah, which is
paralleled by מנחות Menachos as it is by זבחים. Zevachim. But we
are dealing with the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says
שלא לשמה shlo lishmah is actually not really a problem by a
מנחה Mincha because it's self-evident that it's inaccurate, that if you have
a thought about one type of a מנחה Mincha like a dry
one and you're dealing with a wet one or a fried one
and a baked one, it's clearly false. So therefore your intent is
not a problem, which makes a lot of sense. But then you
have to contrast it to another statement of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
basically
compared it to a חטאת Chatas and an אשם Asham and he
said that a שלא לשמה shlo lishmah intent does invalidate. So how
do you reconcile? So now we're dealing with רבא Rava's answer, which
takes רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon at his word basically, because we'll see
the other two resolutions are a real re-reading of the literal meaning
of what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying. And רבא Rava says,
'Yeah, normally a שלא לשמה shlo lishmah isn't meaningful because it's contradicted
by the reality. And when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it is
meaningful, that's when it's an intention of a different owner.' So now
what the גמרא Gemara is doing is it's going through and saying,
'Wait a minute, so you're telling me every time the intent is
contradicted by the reality, it's meaningless? Aren't there other scenarios like this,
not just by מנחה? Mincha? Like isn't there a case like this
by birds? Isn't there a case like this by other things?' And
that's what we're going to spend a lot of today's דף daf
doing, or at least the first עמוד, amud, is showing shouldn't there
be other cases that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says your intent doesn't
matter because the reality contradicts it. So yesterday we had one case
with birds, when the bird was being done below and it was
with intent for a type of a bird, you know, it was
a חטאת, Chatas, it was being done below and it was an
intent to treat it as an עולה. Olah. Doesn't the, isn't it
sort of self-evident that it's not an עולה? Olah? And the answer
is basically, 'Okay, you're right. Maybe in that case your intent wouldn't
matter for רבי שמעון.' Rabbi Shimon. So now we're going to continue
to go through examples where for that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon should
really say your intent doesn't matter if he really goes by this
approach that when the reality contradicts it, we ignore your intent. Yes,
Michael.
But in general, don't we say intent really does matter? Let's say
I want, it's like a ליל סדר, Lail Seder, if I'm not
thinking anything that's one thing, but if I know like I'm eating
מצה matzah but I don't want to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה
mitzvah of מצה, matzah, I'm not יוצא.
yotzei. Alright, that's a different question. That's a question about being יוצא
yotzei and כוונה לשמה kavana lishmah and whatever, it's a different category.
Here it's a question about what type of an intent like invalidates.
So, you know, I mean, I don't know,
look you can't make those comparisons across the board, right? Here there's
a specific question about, you know, כוונה kavana by קרבנות korbanos and
כוונה לפסול, kavana l'pasul, it's not a question whether a כהן kohen
was יוצא yotzei his מצוה mitzvah or whether it somehow invalidated the
sacrifice.
But anyway, but let's say you talk something that was, but that's
also not patently false. Let's say somebody took a לולב lulav and
he says, 'I am right now waving a chicken.' Right? Would that
necessarily mean that he's not יוצא yotzei his מצוה? mitzvah?
If you don't have כוונה kavana for the מצוה mitzvah you're not
יוצא, yotzei, but
if you have כוונה kavana for something else you are already יוצא.
yotzei. I'm not saying anything. I don't know what those cases, every
category of הלכה halacha is different. But here it's not a question
about being יוצא yotzei or not anyway. So let's take a look.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues on ג' עמוד א', gimmel amud
aleph, about five lines down, two dots. קדשי קדשים ששחטן בצפון לשם
קדשים קלים, לירצו. Kodshei kodashim she'shachtan be-tzafon l'shem kodashim kalim, lirtzu.
So wait a minute, so according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if
we ignore it when it's patently false, so when you שחט shacht
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, now this is a, this is like a
softball question and then we'll get to the harder ones. Okay. So
if you שחט shacht קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim in the north and,
you know, a חטאת Chatas and you're שחטינג shachting it in the
north and you're having intent that it's a שלמים, Shelamim, so then
that שלמים Shelamim intention should not invalidate because it's clearly not a
שלמים Shelamim because you're in the north. מעשה מוכיח עליהם דקדשי קדשים
נינהו. Ma'aseh mochiach aleihem d'kodshei kodashim ninhu. The fact that you're in
the north shows that it's not a שלמים. Shelamim. So that's like
I said, that's a softball question. דקדשים קלים בדרום הוי עביד להו,
De'kodashim kalim badarom havi avid lehu, because if it was, if it
was a שלמים, Shelamim, you would be doing it in the south.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אימא דאמר רחמנא אף בדרום.
eima d'amar rachmana af badarom. The גמרא Gemara says that a שלמים
Shelamim is allowed to even be in the south. בדרום ולא בצפון
מי אמר? Badarom v'lo b'tzafon mi amar? It doesn't have to be
in the south. It's not that it's not allowed to be in
the north. So שחטינג shachting something in the north לשם שלמים l'shem
Shelamim is not patently false. It could be a שלמים Shelamim in
the north. דתנן, שחיטתן בכל מקום בעזרה. Detnan, shechitasan b'chol makom ba'azarah.
You could שחט shacht them wherever you want. Okay, fine. That was
a softball question. That was to get to the next question. קדשים
קלים ששחטן בדרום לשום קדשי קדשים, Kodashim kalim she'shachtan badarom l'shum kodshei
kodashim, you have your שלמים Shelamim and you're שחטינג shachting it on
the south side of the מזבח mizbeach and you're doing it with
the intent of let's say a חטאת. Chatas. Okay. So it's clearly
not a שחיטת חטאת shechitas Chatas because if it were a חטאת,
Chatas, it would be in the north. So that כוונה kavana should
not invalidate. Okay, לירצו. lirtzu. מעשה מוכיח עליהם דקדשים קלים נינהו. Ma'aseh
mochiach aleihem d'kodashim kalim ninhu. The act makes it clear that it's
a שלמים, Shelamim, it's not a חטאת, Chatas, it's in the south.
So your intent of a חטאת Chatas should not invalidate. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמי קדשי קדשים נינהו ומעוה הוא דעבר ושחט להו
בדרום.
ami kodshei kodashim ninhu u'ma'aveh hu d'avar
v'shachat lehu badarom. גמרא Gemara says,
look,
you're right. If it were a חטאת, Chatas, it should be in
the north. But that doesn't, it's not that the שחטינג shachting of
an animal in the south is self-evidently not the שחטינג shachting of
a חטאת. Chatas. You know, it could be that an accident happened,
it could be that it is the south even though it is
a חטאת Chatas that Happened in the south,
even though it's a חטאת chatas which should be in the north.
So that's a little bit funny now because then it's like, wait
a minute, so if things could act- so if you're including in
a case where your כוונה kavana is meaningful that this scenario could
happen by accident by the thing that you're having intent of, so
then then now we should include everything. Right, so let's say when
you have intent that it's a dry מנחה mincha and it's really
a wet one, well, it's possible you had you made a נדר
vow of a dry מנחה mincha and you accidentally added oil. Or
you have intent that it's a fried one and it's a baked
one. Well, maybe your כוונה kavana was a- you know, maybe it
was supposed to be a baked מנחה mincha but accidentally you fried
it. I mean, everything could be accidentally. Okay, so once you're allowing
that the כוונה kavana is not meaningless since it is a- since
scenarios exist where mistakes are made and therefore a שחיטה shechita in
the- in the south could be a שחיטה shechita of a חטאת,
chatas, just an accidental שחיטה shechita of a חטאת, chatas, so it's
not a meaningless intent that it's a חטאת chatas because those things
do happen, so then there goes the whole of- categories of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Well, let's just see the גמרא Gemara ask that
question.
Right, so what are we seeing then? That what? That therefore if
you did do this, you are יוצא? yotze?
You invalidate. No, it's the opposite. Once this type of a thing
is a- is a feasible scenario, then your כוונה kavana is meaningful
and therefore your כוונה kavana invalidates. Right?
So then nothing, so then it's like you've just done- so it's
not good for anything, this- this קורבן.
korban. It- well, what do you mean it's not good? So if
you שחט shechted a- let's say I don't know, an אשם asham
in the- well, what's the case? You שחט shechted a- a שלמים
shelamim in the south לשם חטאת, l'shem chatas, so it would be
לא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה, lo ala l'ba'alim l'shem hova, that would
be a- that would be a- that would be a meaningful שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo and it would say, you know, and it would
say that the כ- that the- that the קורבן korban is כשר
kosher but לא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה. lo ala l'ba'alim l'shem hova.
But what is it? It's a- what do you mean what is
it?
It's a קורבן what?
It's a שלמים. shelamim. That's- yeah, that's what we've always been saying.
Yeah, Michael.
Yeah, so that answer might depend on whether it's a male animal
or female animal.
Well, we're going to get to that too. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, but now what we're saying is that
for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said we
ignore your bad intent if it's not feasible, if it's not- if
it's self-evidently wrong, we say, well, even if it's self-evidently wrong, we
don't necessarily ignore it and maybe it actually is a problematic- if
that thing is- if- if mistakes could be made and those things
can happen. So mistakes could always be made, which is what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say. So then every intent should be
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי מחבת
לשם מרחשת נמי.
i hachi machvas l'shem
marcheshes nami.
So if somebody when they were doing the קמיצה kemitza of a
מחבת, machavas, you know, like of- of something frying that since it
was like a bubbling type of a- you know, very heavily oiled
bubbling type of a thing. So that shouldn't invalidate- I mean, that
should invalidate, that should be a problem and don't say it's obviously
wrong because it could be that it was a mistake was made.
So it could be that this is a מרחשת marcheshes נמי. nami.
האי דקקמיץ ליה למרחשת אמרי האי במרחשת נדר. hai de-kakameitz lei l'marcheshes
amri hai be-marcheshes nadar. Right,
the whole point we're saying is, well, your כוונה kavana that it's
a מרחשת marcheshes is feeli- is clearly false because it's a מחבת.
machvas. No, maybe it actually was נדר vowed as the מרחשת marcheshes
and maybe you accidentally made it as a מחבת. machavat. So when
you're having intent and saying I'm doing this as a מרחשת, marcheshes,
maybe it really is a מרחשת marcheshes according to- you know, מנחה,
mincha, right? So it's not a meaningless intent.
במרחשת נדר והדר מייתי ליה במחבת. be-marcheshes nadar ve-hadar maysei lei be-machvas.
So one minute, isn't it self-obviously not a מרחשת marcheshes because you're
bringing it in a מחבת? machvas? Okay, so no, that was a
mistake. דמרחשת הוא מעבר הוא דעבר ואייתי במחבת, de-marcheshes hu me-ava hu
de-avar ve-aysei be-machvas, they accidentally brought it in a מחבת. machvas. So
again, so the point is is that what we're saying is for
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if your intent is obviously wrong then it's
not a problem. And therefore it's not a problem by מנחות minchas
because it's obviously wrong. But then the גמרא Gemara is saying, but
if you allow for the possibility of mistakes, right, so it's not
obviously wrong. You have intent for a מרחשת, marcheshes, okay, here, let's
say here's your- okay, here's your- okay, here's your- here's your מרחשת,
marcheshes, right, which is- which and as opposed to here's your I
guess מחבת. machvas. I guess I don't know why I'm making like
a thingy out of it or whatever. Okay, anyway, here's your מרחשת
marcheshes which is very bubbly, okay, it's got a lot of oil
and here's your מחבת machvas which is flatter, I think this is
correct. Okay, anyway, okay, so anyway, that's your מנחה. mincha. So here
you are, you're the כהן kohen
and you're doing your קמיצה kemitza from the מחבת machvas and you're
thinking in your head, oh, this is a מרחשת. marcheshes. Okay, so
we say that's obviously wrong and therefore your intent is no good
because look, it's a מחבת, machvas, okay. So was that the case?
So or did I reverse it? You have it the right way.
I understand but I want to make it the same.
אי הכי מחבת לשם מרחשת. i hachi machvas l'shem marcheshes. Yeah, okay.
So so the גמרא Gemara is saying is, so you see that
it's obviously wrong so your intent shouldn't be a problem.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying how do you know? Maybe actually
this is a מרחשת. marcheshes. Maybe you took a נדר vow to
bring a מרחשת, marcheshes, you made a mistake and you brought a
מחבת. machvas. So when you're actually thinking that it's a מרחשת, marcheshes,
okay, you're
actually actually thinking like it's actually that scenario could happen. A scenario
could happen that somebody could have said he's going to bring a
מרחשת marcheshet and he winds up bringing a מחבת. machavat. So could
scenario could happen that a מחבת machavat is being brought and it
really is a קרבן korban מרחשת marcheshet that was done wrong, okay?
Scenario number one is this is a מחבת machavat done right.
That's scenario number one. Scenario number two is that this is a
מרחשת marcheshet that was done wrong. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is
saying is if we're allowing for the possibility that sometimes things are
done wrong and that makes her intent meaningful, when the guy has
a intent for a מחבת machavat לשם l'shem מרחשת, marcheshet, why do
you say oh obviously it's a מחבת machavat not מרחשת, marcheshet, we
throw out his intent? No, sometimes there are scenarios where this was
a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong, and therefore the intent that this is
a מרחשת marcheshet is not a blatantly wrong intent, because there are,
maybe it's one in a million, but there are scenarios where this
actually is a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong. So his intent that he's
treating as a מרחשת, marcheshet, it does, it is not a מרחשת,
marcheshet, it is a מחבת. machavat. But his intent that he's treating
as a מרחשת marcheshet should be problematic enough to invalidate, because there
are scenarios, could be one in a million, but there are scenarios
where this actually is a wrong מרחשת. marcheshet. And therefore when he's
thinking of it as a מרחשת, marcheshet, it's not a stupid intent,
it's not a meaningless intent, and should be enough to invalidate. Okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So let's see what it says.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says התם נמי, hasham nami, no there too,
כי נמי במרחשת נדר, ki nami b'marcheshet nadar, even if that was
a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong in that scenario, כי מייתי ליה במחבת
מחבת היא. ki maisi lei b'machavat machavat hi. As soon as you
bring it in a מחבת, machavat, you turn it into a מחבת.
machavat. So this thing, whatever you initially vowed, when you brought for
this case, when you bring it in the end in a מחבת,
machavat, its physical reality defines what type of a קרבן korban it
is. Okay, and therefore whenever you have an intent that you're treating
this as a מרחשת, marcheshet, it's a wrong intent, because even if
this thing was a מרחשת marcheshet that started as a מרחשת marcheshet
and was brought as a מחבת, machavat, at the end of the
day it is a מחבת. machavat. So your intent as a מרחשת
marcheshet is always, right, not in sync with what.
We don't say the same thing by the קרבן korban if you
started doing two מחשבות, machshavot, one above and one below?
Well no, but let's just take the case the גמרא Gemara before.
If you sanctify something as an אשם asham and you bring it
at the south and you שחט shecht it in the south, you're
שחטing shecht an אשם asham in the wrong place. So therefore in
that case, right, in that case it could be that when you
are doing a שלמים shelamim in the south לשם אשם, leshem asham,
there are some scenarios that you would actually have been doing an
אשם asham, in the south. Okay, so doing a שלמים shelamim in
the south לשם l'shem אשם asham is not an absurd intent because
there are scenarios where there might be an אשם asham that was
accidentally being done in the south. But there's no scenario that you're
bringing this and it's actually a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong, because even
if it were a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong, at this stage it's
a מחבת. machavat. So in this case your intent to treat it
as a מרחשת marcheshet is clearly off-base and therefore not a problem,
because there are scenarios where this actually is a wrong מרחשת. marcheshet.
According to רש"י? Rashi? Well, according to, now the גמרא Gemara saying
according to everyone. Let's take a look.
Okay, so התם נמי, hasham nami, התם כי נמי במרחשת נדר כי
מייתי ליה במחבת מחבת הוי. hasham ki nami b'marcheshet nadar ki maisi
lei b'machavat machavat havi. As soon as you bring it in a
מחבת machavat it becomes a
מחבת. machavat. כדתנן, kidnan, האומר הרי עלי במחבת והביא במרחשת מרחשת והביא
במחבת מה שהביא הביא וידי נדרו לא יצא. ha-omer harei alai b'machavat
v'hevi b'marcheshet marcheshet v'hevi b'machavat mah shehevi hevi v'yedei nidro lo yatza.
So you don't, it's the קרבן korban is defined in the end
by what's brought. Now you didn't fulfill your obligation because you said
you're going to bring a מחבת machavat and you brought a מרחשת
marcheshet or vice versa. But what you, your vow doesn't determine the
nature of the קרבן. korban. The קרבן korban is defined by the
physical reality of what it is. Okay, so now what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is is that whenever something here is brought in
a מחבת, machavat, it is by definition whatever your initial vow was,
it by definition is a מחבת. machavat. So therefore a guy here
who has intent that I'm treating this as a מרחשת, marcheshet, there
is no scenario that this is ever a מרחשת. marcheshet. It's not
even a מרחשת marcheshet done wrong. A מרחשת marcheshet done wrong makes
it a מחבת. machavat. So therefore his intent that it's a מרחשת
marcheshet is completely off-base, and the physical reality makes it clear that
it's a מחבת. machavat. You can imagine no scenario that this is
the physical reality and that this is a מרחשת. marcheshet. And since
in every single scenario in the world this scenario is a מחבת,
machavat, his intent as a מרחשת marcheshet is meaningless and does not
invalidate. As opposed to when he שחטs shecht a שלמים shelamim in
the south לשם l'shem אשם, asham you can imagine a scenario that
an אשם asham, is being שחטed shecht in the south. And therefore
that כוונה kavana is meaningful enough to create a problem because that
scenario does exist. It's done incorrectly but it does exist. So therefore
that's not a meaningless intent. This as a מרחשת marcheshet is a
meaningless intent. Yes, Charlie.
It's potentially meaningful, but only if the animal's a male.
We're getting there. You said that before, we're getting there. Okay, alright,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
ודלמא אמר זו להביא במחבת והביא
במרחשת *V'dilma amar zo l'havi b'machavat v'heivi b'marcheshet*. One minute. If you
say הרי עלי במחבת *harei alai b'machavat* and you bring in a
מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet*, your vow doesn't determine the identity. The identity is
determined by the physical reality. But let's say you have some flour
and oil in front of you and you say, "This flour and
oil I'm going to bring, I am sanctifying this as a מנחה
mincha מחבת machvas, *mincha machavat*," okay, this flour and oil. And then
you go ahead and you bring it in a מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet*.
So that's a scenario where you've already designated the flour and the
oil, okay, you designated it as one and you brought it as
the other. So that case it is a מרחשת marcheshes. *marcheshet* done
wrong, right? Because that's how it was sanctified. And what's the הלכה
halakha *halacha*? אבל זו להביא במחבת והביא במרחשת מרחשת marcheshes, והביא במחבת
הרי זו פסולה *Aval zo l'havi b'machavat v'heivi b'marcheshet marcheshet v'heivi b'machavat
harei zo pesulah*. You actually it is invalid. Okay, so if you
just say I'm taking a vow of a מחבת machvas. *machavat* and
you bring a מרחשת marcheshes. *marcheshet*, fine, that's your personal vow of
a מחבת machvas, *machavat*, but this is a מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet* because
you brought it as a מרחשת marcheshes. *marcheshet*. But if you say
I'm sanctifying this flour and oil as a מחבת machvas. *machavat* and
you bring it as a מרחשת marcheshes, *marcheshet*, guess what? You did
a מחבת machvas. *machavat* incorrectly and you invalidated it. So there is
a scenario where this מחבת machvas *machavat* is a מרחשת marcheshes? *marcheshet*
done incorrectly. Okay, it's invalid, but when you said you sanctified the
oil as מחבת machvas, *machavat* and you brought it as מרחשת mercheses
*marcheshet*, it is defined as a מרחשת marcheshes, *marcheshet* done incorrectly. So
such a scenario exists. The same way scenarios exist done wrong where
a חטאת chatas *chatas* is שחט shecht *shechted* in the south and
therefore it's invalid, there's a scenario where a מרחשת marcheshes, *marcheshet* is
brought as a מחבת machvas, *machavat* and therefore invalid. So when you
by this מחבת machavas *machavat* has intent of a מרחשת marcheshes *marcheshet*,
it's not a meaningless intent, because there is a scenario where this
is a מרחשת *marcheshet* done wrong and invalid. But again, that just
means your intent is not completely off base. Such scenarios do exist
in the world. Okay. So now we have a problem. Why does
רבי שמעון Reb Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* say we get to discard your
intent because it's clearly
wrong? This intent actually there are
scenarios, scenarios that came through mistakes, but once we're allowing the case
of coming through mistakes, okay, a scenario of a מרחשת *marcheshet* done
as a מחבת machavas *machavat* exists and therefore your intent that it's
a מרחשת *marcheshet* should be a meaningful intent and should invalidate it.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says זו להביא במחבת והביא במרחשת
מרחשת והביא במחבת הרי זו פסולה *Zo l'havi b'machavat v'heivi b'marcheshet marcheshet
v'heivi b'machavat harei zo pesulah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הרבנן
הכי נמי hachi nami. *ha-Rabbanan hachi nami*. You know what, for the
rabbis you're right. That scenario exists and therefore that should create a
challenge for רבי שמעון Reb Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. Why do we ignore
your intent? Such an intent is not completely meaningless. But רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*, כיון דאמר רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *kivan d'amar
Rabbi Shimon*, it's the same רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* we're
dealing with actually says in this scenario of the מנחה mincha *mincha*
that you you sanctify it for one thing and you bring it
for another, you know what he says? אף ידי נדרו יצא *af
yedei nidro yatza*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* actually says if
you come along and you say, right, here's my flour and you
say here's my flour, here's your flour I guess and here's your
oil, I don't know why I'm drawing it like this, anyway, here's
your flour and here's your oil and you say, "I'm going to
bring this as a מרחשת *marcheshet*," okay, הרי זו למרחשת *harei zo
l'marcheshet*. And then you bring it as a מחבת machvas *machavat*. You
did it wrong. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* actually says that
you fulfilled your obligation. That this
actually... Okay, now why could you fulfill your obligation if it's a
מחבת machvah *machavat*, you said למרחשת *l'marcheshet*? No, but but then you
didn't fulfill your you didn't fulfill your נדר *neder*, you said הרי
זו למרחשת *harei zo l'marcheshet*. So what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon* actually says is this phrase הרי זו למרחשת *harei zo l'marcheshet*
for some reason, even though that's your verbal sanctity, you can sanctify
something as a חטאת chatas *chatas*, as an אשם asham *asham*, as
an עולה olah *olah*, but as a מנחה mincha *mincha*, you know
sort of like you know the הלכה *halacha* by the birds that
the כהן kohen *kohen* gets to determine its identity. He basically says
that your vow basically gets translated as what we translate this as
is הרי זו למנחה *harei zo l'mincha*. Okay. And what type of
a מנחה mincha *mincha* it's going to be is going to be
defined by what gets brought at the end. So for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*, when you bring a מחבת machavas *machavat*, whatever
you said up here, whatever you said even if you sanctified the
object directly, in the end all you did was you made it
a מנחה mincha *mincha*. And the type of קרבן korban. *korban* it
is is always defined by what it is at the end, which
is a מחבת *machavat*.
Wait, wouldn't we say that by a קרבן korban. *korban*? הרי זו
לאשם *harei zo l'asham* and it turned
out as an עולה olah *olah*? Those are fundamentally different categories, right?
There's אשם asham *asham*, there's חטאת chatas, *chatas*, there's עולה olah *olah*,
whereas here the basic category is מנחה mincha *mincha*. So it's only
the question of
physically... well, first of all it's not true because the תורה Torah
*Torah* obviously puts them in different categories and the other is sub-categories.
But anyway, but also the תורה *Torah* also says, you know, I
think if the language of the תורה *Torah* by the מנחה mincha
*mincha* by these מנחות minchos *minchas* is if you bring it this
way. It's not about how you sanctify it, right? Isn't that the
language by the מנחות minchos *minchas*? What's it say by the מנחות
minchos, *minchas*? It says, it says... אם זבח zevach,
שלמים, shelamim ואם
מנחה, ve'im minchah, ואם, ve'im,
yeah, you're right, points out, כל המנחה, kol haminchah,
וכי מנחת מחבת קרבנך, vechi minchas machavas korbanecha, maybe not, וכי מנחת
המרחשת קרבנך. vechi minchas hamarcheshes korbanecha. So maybe not, maybe that sounds
a little bit like it's the identity of the קרבן. korban? Anyway,
I don't know the answer, but he says once it's a מחבת,
whatever you sanctify it at all, it's a מחבת. So there's no
scenario for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that this is a מרחשת done
wrong. No matter how you sanctified it, when you brought it as
a מחבת, it's a מחבת. And therefore, it works out very well
that any intent for him as something else is clearly a wrong
an off-base intent and therefore we ignore it. And there's no scenario
where that intent of מרחשת reflects the reality, because you can imagine
no scenario of what happened before that this is a מרחשת. This
is always a מחבת. As opposed to, if you שחט shecht a
שלמים shlamim, in the south לשם חטאת leshem chatas or לשם l'shem
אשם, asham? you can imagine a scenario where this is a חטאת
chatas or אשם asham done in the south. But here where you
have intent that this is a מרחשת, there's no scenario in the
world where this was a מרחשת. Whatever you said before, if this
is how it's brought, it's a מחבת at the end of the
day. Right, let's just read that. כיון דאמר רבי שמעון אף ידי
נדר יצא, אלמא קביעותא דמנא לא כלום היא. keivan de'amar Reb Shimon
af yedei neder yatza, alma kvi'usa demanei lo klum hi. When you
now the קביעותא kvi'usa is not the קביעותא kvi'usa of the כלי
kli when you make it, when you make the vow according to
a particular vessel, that's meaningless. לא שנא אמר זו ולא שנא אמר
עלי. lo shna amar zo velo shna amar alai. Okay, so now
we're still back to where we said, which is for רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, when what you say is clearly off-base, it does not
invalidate. However, what we've allowed for is, if it's not if such
a what you're saying, your intent actually could be a scenario by
mistake, it's a meaningful enough intent to invalidate. So the idea that
I'm saying this is a חטאת chatas that I'm doing in the
south, that's possible that that happens by mistake, and therefore could invalidate.
But saying this is a מרחשת could never happen. Any scenario you
could imagine, once it's brought in a מחבת, it'll never be a
מרחשת. So I don't care whether yes mistakes, no mistakes, and therefore
since this is impossible, your intent of מרחשת, it does not invalidate.
Yes?
So let me understand this, so like, you know, these are done
in the pan, whatever, so let's say you say הרי עלי למחבת,
harei alai lamachvas, let's say, then the כהן kohen treats it as
a חוטא chotei and then you just doesn't put in, you know,
any water, he doesn't whatever, then could the כהן kohen ruin it
in that scenario? Because it's not in either it's not in
a מחבת, it's neither in a... Well, that's different. You can't bring
a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei if somebody isn't חייב מנחת חוטא. chayav
minchas chotei. That's not בר נדר. bar neder.
So then that means the כהן then ruined it if he treats
it as a חוטא, chotei, right?
Yeah, but that's... yeah, yeah.
Are these two types of מנחות minchos offerings brought for particular
reasons, one or the other?
No. The different types, that's sort of what Mike was asking. The
case you have about different reasons why they're brought is only by
a מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. But all these different types of ways
of making it, there's no the תורה never assigned any different context
in which one type is brought over another. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
אלא מעתה ella me'ata says
the גמרא, Gemara finally we get to Charlie's question, עולה ששחטה לשם
חטאת תרצה, olah sheshachtah leshem chatas tirtzeh,
if you שחט shecht an עולה olah? for a חטאת, chatas, that
should be
good, דהאי דכר והאי נקבה. dehai duchar vehai nekeivah. One is a
male and one is a female.
An עולה olah... is a male and a חטאת chatas. is a
female. Okay, so if you're שוחט shechting an עולה לשם חטאת, olah
leshem chatas, so then clearly you're off-base. Okay, now presumably and you
can't say well maybe you made a mistake and sanctified it the
wrong way, because then like it still wouldn't be like fit for
הקרבה hakravah here, you know, so it's, you know, wouldn't really be
a I mean it's one thing something's already a חטאת chatas. and
you're doing it in the south. But if you sanctified a female
a male as a חטאת, chatas right, it's never really a חטאת.
chatas, I mean you have to redeem the money and whatever, there's
ways of dealing with it. So this case is clearly it's clearly
wrong and it's not like oh an accident happened, because if an
accident happened it wouldn't even be a חטאת. chatas So therefore that
should be clearly wrong and it should not invalidate. So the גמרא
Gemara says, כיון דאיכא שעיר נשיא דדכר הוא לא ידיעא. keivan de'ika
se'ir nasi dedachar hu lo yedi'a. Ah, so the גמרא Gemorah, says,
when you say, okay I didn't see what he said, when you
said an עולה לשם חטאת, olah leshem chatas, it's not obviously false
because there are some there is a חטאת chatas that is a
male, a goat of a of a נשיא. nasi. So the גמרא
Gemorah says, okay, so so the
גמרא Gemorah says, אמר לשם חטאת יחיד מאי איכא למימר? amar leshem
chatas yachid mai ika lemeimar? So let's say the guy said I
am שוחט shechting this male עולה olah whatever, I am שוחט shechting
it for a private חטאת, chatas okay? So it's clearly a false
intent.
ותניא חטאת יחיד ששחטה לשם עולה תרצה? vesu chatas yachid sheshachtah leshem
olah tirtzeh? How about a a female חטאת chatas that you שחט
shechted as an עולה? olah, An עולה... olah? was only male, דחטאת
נקבה ועולה זכר. de'chatas nekeivah v'olah zachar. Okay, so therefore, says the
גמרא, Gemorah and again, this is a case where you can't say,
"Well, sometimes again, mistakes are made that you because because then it
wouldn't actually be that animal. It's not like, you know, so so
so this should clearly be a false and a wrong intent. This
clearly is not an עולה olah? if it's a female. So the
גמרא Gemorah says,
מחסיה באליה. mechasyah b'alyah. So now we get a little funny because
now the question seems to be much more a question about appearances
rather than about the objective realities or possibilities. The גמרא Gemorah says,
"You know what is true, that this חטאת chatas, can't be an
עולה, olah but not everybody sees that it's, you know, this... wait,
what's the case whether a חטאת chatas can be an עולה? olah,
Which is the immediate one we're dealing
with? Whether a חטאת chatas can be an
עולה? olah So the... so the גמרא Gemorah says that this חטאת,
chatas. it's not obvious that it's a female because it's got a
fat tail. And since it's got a fat tail, or the opposite,
or you know, sometimes an עולה olah I guess isn't obvious that
it's a male because it's got a fat tail. And therefore, when
you see somebody שוחט-ing shochet a חטאת chatas לשם עולה, leshem olah,
it's not obvious to you that, "Wait a minute, this is a
female, it can't be an עולה," olah you know, because you'll say...
because you're not able to immediately see whether it's male or female
because of the fat tail. Which is again pretty funny because that
makes it sound like it's a whole מראית עין maris ayin thing.
As opposed to like, objectively, is this intent meaningful because does this
scenario ever exist, which is an objective type of a question. Here
we're actually talking about will people perceive it as obviously false. And
the answer is this won't be perceived as obviously false because people
won't be able to see if it's male or female because of
the fat tail.
Which is interesting because are the people really looking this close, you
know what I mean?
I understand. I mean, whatever, we're looking through people's eyes, but the
חידוש chiddush is still that we're looking through their eyes and it's
not a question of objectively. So the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא היכא
דאייתי כיבשה. hani nicha heicha de'aisi kivsah. That's if you brought a
sheep, so therefore it's got a fat tail so you could say
people can't tell whether it's male or female so it's not obviously
wrong. Okay, but אייתי שעירה מאי איכא למימר? aisi seirah mai ika
lemeimar? If you brought a goat that doesn't have a fat tail,
it would be obviously wrong if you're שוחט-ing shochet a חטאת chatas
for an עולה olah, or an עולה olah for a חטאת. chatas
So, אלא בין זכר לנקבה לאו אדעתיה דאינשי. ela bein zachar l'nekeivah
lav adateih de'inshi. Okay, which once again says explicitly that it's a
question of people's perception. Yeah, nobody pays attention to animals if they're
male or female. Nobody's looking. Okay, which is like, as Michael says,
so people are looking if it's a מחבת or a מרחשת? I
mean, who knows? So now it becomes... I mean, this one is
just the claim about what people are paying attention to, which is
okay, whatever, say what you will. But the funny thing here is
that now what makes your intent meaningful or not is like within
the particular, you know, cultural or anthropological context, societal context in which
you exist, right? When I say this, is it self-evident to people,
were people here and looking, would it be self-evident that it was
wrong? Okay, so that's sort of the measure. Not the measure is
like, is it clearly false based on the reality, but would it
be clearly wrong based on somebody who was observing it? And that
somehow now is the standard. So if through the observer's eyes it's
clearly wrong, then it's not a problem. If the observer's eyes they
don't pay attention to those things and it's not clearly wrong, then
it is a meaningful negative intent. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
פסח ששחטו לשם אשם וירצה. pesach she'shechato leshem asham ve'yirtzeh. How about
a פסח pesach that was שוחט-ed shochet for the sake of an
אשם? asham, Although they're both males, דהאי בן שנה והאי בן שתיים.
de'hai ben shanah ve'hai ben shtayim. פסח pesach is one year old
and an אשם asham. is two years old. Give me a break,
if people aren't paying attention between male and female, you think they're
paying attention between one year and two years? So the גמרא Gemara
says, כיון דאיכא אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע לא פסיקא ליה. keivan de'ika
asham nazir ve'asham metzora lo pasika lei. No, because there are some
אשמות ashamos that are one year, so when you say a פסח
pesach for an אשם, asham you might mean a one year אשם.
asham So אמר לשום אשם גזילות לשום אשם מעילות מאי איכא למימר?
amar leshum asham gezeilos leshum asham meilos mai ika lemeimar? Let's say
you're explicit for the... you say for the sake of an אשם
גזילות asham gezeilos or אשם מעילות asham meilos which is a two
year... asham, so why that shouldn't be a problem, because it should
be obviously wrong. ותו אשם גזילות ואשם מעילות ששחטו לשם פסח לירצו?
Ve-su asham gezeilos ve-asham me'ilos she-shachato leshem Pesach lirzu? Let's say you
take a two-year אשם asham, that you שחט shechted for a פסח.
Pesach. דאורייתא פסח בן שנה והני בני שתי שנים. De-oraisa Pesach ben
shana vehanei benei shtei shanim. אלא בין שנה לבין שתי שנים לאו
אדעתיה דאינשי. Ella bein shana levein shtei shanim lav adaiteih de-inshei. People
don't pay attention to one year, two years. Now why does the
גמרא Gemara think that that's more obvious? Well maybe because again for
male or female you have to look more closely at the genitalia,
but one year, two years maybe just a size issue. So maybe
the גמרא Gemara said that maybe should be obvious to people, right,
big or small. So the גמרא Gemara says no, even that's not
obvious. דאיכא בן שנה דמיחזי כבן שתי שנים. de-ika ben shana de-michzei
ke-ven shtei shanim. Sometimes one-year-olds are more mature for their age and
they look like they're two years old. ואיכא בן שתי שנים דמיחזי
כבן שנה, ve'ika ben shtei shanim de-michzei ke-ven shana, and two-year-olds one-year-olds.
So it's interesting, right, the גמרא Gemara thought that people wouldn't be
paying attention to the sex and the genitalia but they would more
obviously immediately see the age.
Because he may have like better horns, you know.
I understand. Right. So the גמרא Gemara says no, even there not
necessarily so. So again now in order to defend רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon look, רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's logic is a very good logic
but because the question is that if we then apply that logic
there's a lot of cases about animal sacrifices that כוונה kavana shouldn't
be a problem, we're now redefining it to say that it's only
not a problem when A, it's like you know the intent is
not when the intent is not obviously wrong through the eyes of
people, okay, but it's defined as whether people will see that it's
obviously wrong. So by the מנחה mincha people will see it's obviously
wrong whereas other things it might be it might be wrong objectively,
clearly wrong, but it won't be obviously wrong through the eyes of
people. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
שעיר ששחטו לשם אשם לירצי? Se'ir she-shachato leshem asham lirtzi? Now an
אשם asham, should only be a sheep. So let's say you שחט
shechted a goat as an אשם, that should obviously be wrong.
דהאי צמר ודהאי שיער. De-hai tzemer ve-de-hai se'ar. One has wool and
the other has hair, like people could obviously see the difference between
a goat and a sheep. So the גמרא Gemara says even I
can tell the difference between a goat and a sheep. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמרי דכרא אוכמא הוא. Amri dichra uchma hu. No,
people won't know it, they'll say you know they'll say that it's
like even if it's a goat they'll say yeah it's just like
a dark-looking sheep, it's a dark-looking ram, it's a black goat of
the family, black sheep of the family that looks like a goat,
which is pretty funny right
there.
Exactly. Anyway, exactly. עגל ופר ששחטן לשם פסח ואשם לירצו? Egel u-par
she-shechatan leshem Pesach ve-asham lirzu? How about a cow or a calf
שחט shacht for a פסח? Pesach? Everybody can tell the difference between
a cow and a sheep. Okay. דעגל ופר במידי דפסח ואשם ליכא.
De-egel u-par bimidi de-Pesach ve-asham leika. אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami,
says the גמרא, Gemara you know what you're right, finally okay that
case is obviously wrong. Okay, ומאי זבחים רוב זבחים. U-mai zevachim rov
zevachim. Now this answer hopefully allows us to get rid of all
of some of the weaker answers before. It actually says you know
what you're basically right. For רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon maybe there are
cases even by animal sacrifices where bad intent doesn't matter, where your
bad intent is so patently wrong that we forget about it, that
we ignore it. So the same רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that says
bad intent by מנחה mincha doesn't matter because it's obviously contradicted by
the physical reality, he could say the same about bad intent by
certain animal even though he says as opposed to animal sacrifices, he
just means as opposed to most animal sacrifices because most animal sacrifices
you don't know, is this a חטאת chatas or an אשם, is
this an עולה olah or a שלמים, shelamim right, you can't tell.
But when your intent is patently wrong by animal sacrifices as well
we also get to ignore it. Okay, so one case is a
cow or a calf לשם פסח. leshem Pesach. But now that we're
allowing that can exist by animal sacrifices we can go back to
some of our other answers as well and say maybe those also
you know we would get to ignore your intent, right? So male
for female those types of cases you know maybe אין הכי נמי
ein hachi nami we would get to ignore those cases. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so that's one
answer, that's רבא'ס Rava's approach to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon taking רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon at face value that
the reason by a מנחה mincha it doesn't invalidate is because it's
obviously false. And then we went through a whole series of things
where we said wait there are cases by animal sacrifices that are
obviously false and in the end we conceded אין הכי נמי ein
hachi nami there might be some cases of animal sacrifice that רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon also would say your wrong intent is not a
problem, okay, after giving a lot of weak answers about how people
are perceiving it and so on. Now we have a different approach
to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon רבא אמר לא קשיא, Rava amar lo
kashya, it's not difficult, כאן בקומץ מנחה לשום מנחה כאן בקומץ מנחה
לשום זבח. kan be-komatz mincha leshum mincha kan be-komatz mincha leshum zevach.
Meaning the one place רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. says your כוונה kavana
is a problem is not a problem by מנחה mincha and another
case he says it is. כאן בקומץ מנחה לשום מנחה כאן בקומץ
מנחה לשום זבח. Kan be-komatz mincha leshum mincha kan be-komatz mincha leshum
zevach. Now this seems to be exact opposite logic. If you have
an intent of a מנחה mincha, מרחשת for a מחבת it doesn't
invalidate. If as you're taking a מנחה mincha you're saying I'm doing
this as a sheep עולה, olah, okay, then it does invalidate. So
clearly he is not following the previous approach. He clearly he's saying
that your intent could be absurdly wrong and still be a problem.
So an עולה olah for the sake of a מנחה mincha for
the sake of an עולה olah, that invalidates. Okay so if that's
true why does a מנחה mincha, for the sake of a מנחה
mincha not invalidate? You know and the point basically with him though
to start with is that he's the exact opposite of. opposite of
the previous approach. According to him, the more patently false it is,
the more problematic it is. The more it's bad intent and the
more problematic it is. So a מנחה mincha for the sake of
an עולה, olah, that's invalid. So then a מנחה mincha for the
sake of a מנחה, mincha, why is that not invalid? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says:
so מנחה לשם מנחה, mincha leshum mincha, it's not based on the
fact that it's obviously wrong. Obviously wrong, it's still a problem. Maybe
it's even a bigger problem. So why is מנחה mincha for the
sake of a מנחה mincha not a problem? מנחה לשם מנחה mincha
leshum mincha because of וזאת תורת המנחה, vezos toras hamincha, because of
the פסוק. pasuk. This is the law of the מנחה, mincha תורה
אחת לכל המנחות. torah achas lechol haminchos. It puts all the מנחות
minchos in one category. So מנחה mincha, A for the sake of
מנחה mincha. B is not considered שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. It's a
similar point. It's not because it's obviously wrong, it's because it's not
considered שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. Let's say for example, I mean can
you think of let's say I slaughtered an עולה olah, that was
a sheep and I said I'm slaughtering this as a goat עולה,
olah, right? Let's say I said I'm slaughtering this as a goat
עולה, olah. would that invalidate? You say no, it's an עולה, olah,
it's an עולה, olah okay. One guy brings a sheep, one guy
brings a goat, it's a different identity of an עולה. olah So
this type of מנחה mincha and that type of מנחה, mincha they're
all מנחות, minchos it's not considered שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, that's his
reasoning. Not because it's obviously wrong, it could be really obviously wrong
and be a problem, a מנחה mincha for the sake of an
עולה, olah but מנחה mincha A, מנחה mincha. B, it's all the
same מנחה, mincha it's all מנחה. mincha You following? What?
Yeah, it sounds like you're right. That's a little funny because those
are brought for different circumstances. But at the end of the day,
you're not changing its basic name of a קרבן. korban. מנחה mincha
for מנחה mincha, is still the, it's not a שינוי השם. shinuy
hashem. It's still enough in the same category. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says that also makes sense. It's not exactly the words of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. but it makes sense. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says: תורה אחת לכל המנחות. torah achas lechol haminchos. מנחה לשם
זבח mincha leshum zevach וזאת תורת המנחה וזבח לא כתיב. vezos toras
hamincha veze vach lo ksiv. But a מנחה mincha for a זבח,
no, those are clearly different קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says והתנא מפני שמעשיו מוכיחין עליה קאמר. vehatana mipney shemaaseh mocheach aleha
kama. One minute, but the
תנא tanna says the reason isn't because all מנחות minchos are the
same category. The תנא tanna says the reason it's not a problem
when you do one מנחה mincha for another is because it's obviously
wrong. That's the language, the acts make it clear that it's a
different מנחה. mincha So the גמרא Gemara, says: הכי קאמר, hachi kamar,
here's how you read it: אף על גב דמחשבה דלא מינכרא היא
ותיפסל, af al gav demachshavah d'lo minkara hee veteepasel, even though the
intention is not obviously correct, it's a funny way of saying it,
meaning: even though the intention is obviously wrong and therefore should be
a problem. Meaning, until now we were reading because the intention is
obviously wrong, that's why it's not a problem. This way of reading
it is, although all concede when you do a מחבת for a
מרחשת, it's obviously wrong intent and therefore because it's מעשיו מוכיחין עליה,
maaseh mocheach aleha, it should be more of a problem because it's
obviously wrong intent, nevertheless it's not a problem because all מנחות minchos
are one category. וזאת
תורת המנחה, vezos toras hamincha, תורה
אחת לכל המנחות, torah achas lechol haminchos, okay. So basically we ignore
the line that seems to say the reason it's okay is because
it's obviously wrong, and we flip it and we say although it's
obviously wrong and should be a problem, it's okay because all מנחות
minchos are one category. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומאי אף בזבחים
אינו כן? umay af bizvachim eyno kein? What, so then what does
it mean by saying that by זבחים zvachim the הלכה doesn't apply?
That an עולה olah for a שלמים shelamim is no good? אף
גב דשחיטה אחת לכולן af gav deshchita achas lechulan וזאת תורת המנחה
וזבח לא כתיב. vezos toras hamincha veze vach lo ksiv. Again, it's
sort of reading it not as the reason but as like an
even though. Although by זבחים, zvachim,
when you do an עולה ola for a שלמים shelamim it's not
obviously wrong, or an עולה ola for a חטאת chatas it's not
obviously wrong and therefore should be okay, nevertheless it's no good because
you don't have a פסוק pasuk to tell you that you treat
all קרבנות korbanos as one category. Okay, so what you get at
it's basically
like it's confusing because it takes the reason and turns it into
an even though.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says here, okay, so מחבת for מרחשת, the
כוונה kavanah is okay,
מרחשת is okay because מעשיה מוכיחין,
maaseha
mochechin,
and עולה for שלמים shelamim
is no good because שחיטה אחת לכולן. shchita achas lechulan.
Okay, so the simple sense is that this is okay because it's
obviously wrong, and this is a problem because it's not obviously wrong,
right? That's the first way of reading it, right? What we read
was, this is okay, why is this okay? Because all מנחות minchos
are one category. That's really why that's okay, okay because all מנחות
Menachos are one category. Even though it's obviously wrong and that should
make it more פסול, pasul, it's okay because all מנחות Menachos are
one category. So this rather than the reason why it's okay, this
is the even though. It's okay because all מנחות Menachos are one
category. Even though. Okay because all מנחות Menachos are one category, even
though it's obvious, even though it's obviously wrong and that should make
it more פסול, posul, it's okay because all מנחות Menachos are one
category. So this, rather than the reason why it's okay, this is
the even though. It's okay because all מנחות Menachos are one category,
even though it's obviously a wrong כוונה kavana and should be a
bigger problem. Nevertheless, it's okay because one category. This is no good
because these are two categories, and therefore it's no good in a
שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Even though it's not obviously wrong, and therefore
because it's not obviously wrong, maybe it should be not a bigger
problem. Nevertheless, although it's not obviously wrong and shouldn't be a bigger
problem, it's a problem because they're different categories. So we took, we
flipped it. These things which had been the explanation of why this
is good and why this is bad, now everything becomes for this
reason it should be worse. Okay, but it's still good because it's
one category. And for this reason that it's not obviously wrong it
should be better, but it's a problem because they're two separate categories.
Okay, so that was a very creative reread of that ברייתא. braisa.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא מעתה Ela
maata says the גמרא, Gemara חטאת חלב ששחטו לשם חטאת סתם לשם
חטאת עבודה זרה לשם חטאת נזיר לשם חטאת מצורע תכשר ותרצה? chatas
chelev sheshachato leshem chatas stam leshem chatas avoda zara leshem chatas nazir
leshem chatas metzora tichshar v'tertzah?
So as long as we're saying that if you within one category
of קרבנות korbanos it's not considered שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, within different
מנחות Menachos it's not שלא לשמה shelo lishmo because זאת תורת המנחה,
Zos Toras haMincha, so between one type of a חטאת chatas and
another type of a חטאת chatas shouldn't be a problem? It's all
one category and not only that you have a פסוק posuk דאמר
רחמנא וזאת תורת החטאת תורה אחת לכל החטאות. d'amar Rachmana v'zos Toras
haChatas Torah achas l'chol hachataos.
It's a pretty darn good argument. Okay, once we're saying that it's
all based on being one category of קרבנות. korbanos.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לרבי שמעון le'Rebbi Shimon הכי נמי.
You know what, you're right. For רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we would
say that. That we'd say if you had a כוונה kavana for
a different type of a חטאת chatas it wouldn't invalidate the same
way a כוונה kavana for a different type of a מנחה mincha
doesn't invalidate. So the גמרא Gemara. says, דהא אמר—take deha amar out
the word לרבנן, le'rabbanan, there's obviously a question here of the text,
but we're going to take out the word לרבנן—הכא נמי, דהא אמר
רבא, deha amar Rava,
because רבא Rava says, חטאת חלב ששחטו לשם חטאת סתם לשם חטאת
עבודת כוכבים כשירה. chatas chelev sheshachato leshem chatas stam leshem chatas avodas
kochavim k'shira.
Okay, so there, אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. Okay, within רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon between one type of a מנחה Mincha and another
doesn't invalidate, between one type of a חטאת chatas and another also
doesn't invalidate. So the גמרא Gemara says, לשם חטאת נזיר ולשם חטאת
מצורע פסולה דהני היא עולות בהדייהו נינהו. leshem chatas nazir u'leshem chatas
metzora psula d'hanei hee olos bahadeihu ninhu.
But if you did it for the sake of an, of a
חטאת chatas of a נזיר nazir or of a חטאת chatas of
a מצורע, metzora, that would invalidate. Why? Because those are different types
of חטאות. chataos. That's not fundamentally תורת החטאת. Toras haChatas. Why is
that not fundamentally the same קרבן? korban So there's two ways of
reading this. One is דהני עולות נינהו, dahani olos ninhu, those are
effectively עולות. olos. Why are they effectively עולות? olos? Because those are
חטאות chataos that are not about sin, but they're about status related.
So because they're status related they're a different category. That's interesting. So
if you vary between one חטאת chatas of a certain type of
a sin to another, that is all considered one category and it
doesn't invalidate. But between a חטאת chatas, that's more status related that
would be a different category. That's one way of reading it. The
other way of reading it is עולות בהדייהו. olos bahadeihu. Those חטאות
chataos have עולות olos that come with them. And since they're packaged
together with עולות, olos, again they're seen as a different type of
a קרבן. korban Okay, but the basic answer here is that for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the logic here is not is it obviously
false or not obviously false, the logic is within one genre of
קרבן korban. it's not considered שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. And that leads
to the idea that even a variation, varying between one חטאת chatas
and another is not a שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, although there might
be a different genre of חטאת chatas, which is a problem. But
at least within the same genre of חטאת, chatas. like a חטאת
chatas about sin, that actually would not invalidate. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. One minute, says the גמרא. Gemara רב
אחא בריה דרבא מתני לה לכולה לפסולה. Rav Acha brei deRava masni
lei lekula le'psula. ושחט אותה לחטאת לשם אותו חטאת. v'shachat osah le'chatas
leshem oso chatas. רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha brei deRava did
not buy this. He said that maybe presumably even according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon a חטאת חלב chatas chelev that you שחט shecht
for חטאת סתם chatas stam is invalidated. Because by the חטאות chataos
it says ושחט אותה לחטאת, v'shachat osah le'chatas,
it for sin, meaning it has to identify with the particular sin.
So that counterbalances the וזאת תורת החטאת. v'zos Toras haChatas.
Well, then we have to ask which one does which פסוק posuk
though. What? Then don't we have to ask?
Yeah, so thankfully we're not. So again by a מנחה Mincha maybe,
and also it's because the מנחה, Mincha the reasons for bringing the
מנחה Mincha are very generic. Now again Michael asks, how about a
מנחת חוטא? minchas chotei? And why when you switch from one מנחה
Mincha to another that really should maybe have a different identity. But
anyway by a מנחה Mincha in general the פסוקים psukim are much
more generic. So anyway, so there we could say it's all fundamentally
one category. Though I acknowledge Michael's question about the מנחת חוטא. minchas
chotei. Okay, whereas by a חטאת, chatas. even though it's וזאת תורת
החטאת, v'zos Toras haChatas, there really are distinct identities to a חטאת.
chatas And therefore even for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. at least the
second claim is, it's a debate what would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say for one חטאת chatas for a different type of a חטאת.
chatas So according to one opinion it would be like a מנחה
Mincha. and it would not be a problem. And according to this
actually חטאת chatas. would be different and it would be a problem.
Okay, so that is רבא's Rava approach to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon?
Now, where were we? Okay רב אשי אמר לא קשיא. Rav Ashi
amar lo kashya. Here's the third approach to reconciling רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon? When does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say so by a מנחה
Mincha it is a problem and when is it not? According to
one when it's for the sake of the owner's it's a problem
because that's not obviously false and the basic definition for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon when it's okay is when it's obviously false. The second
explanation is when was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. say it's a problem
when you have a מנחה Mincha לשם זבח leshem zevach לשם עולה
leshem olah or שלמים shelamim? or whatever because but when but for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon anytime it's a מנחה Mincha for a different
type of a מנחה Mincha you're going to be okay because all
מנחות minchos are fundamentally one category. That's רבא Rava's approach and now
we get the third approach. So one approach is that it's based
upon whether it's obviously false. The other approach is that it's based
on the idea that all מנחות minchos are fundamentally one category. Now
we have רב אשי Rav Ashi's approach. רב אשי אמר לא קשיא.
Rav Ashi amar lo kashya. כאן בקומץ מנחת מחבת לשם מרחשת Kan
bekometz minchas machavas leshem marcheshes כאן בקומץ מנחת מחבת לשם מנחת מרחשת.
Kan bekometz minchas machavas leshem minchas marcheshes. Okay so so for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon the problem is if you say I'm doing this
frying pan as a deep fry as a whatever as a you
know for as you know with the intent of a deep fryer
so that כוונה kavana is meaningless because you're not defining the identity
of the מנחה Mincha you're just sort of saying what you're how
you're what you're thinking about the כלי kli like like you know
so that's not about the identity you're not saying I'm doing this
מנחת מחבת minchas machavas as a מנחת מרחשת minchas marcheshes your כוונה
kavana is I am doing this thinking of a frying pan okay
that's very nice. Okay so anyway that doesn't invalidate well when you
try to re-identify the nature of the מנחה Mincha. it does invalidate.
So why כאן בקומץ מנחת מחבת לשם מנחת מרחשת? Kan bekometz minchas
machavas leshem minchas marcheshes? מחבת לשם מרחשת במנא קמחשב Machavas leshem marcheshes
b'mana kamachashev מחשבה במנא לא פסלה. machshava bimna lo pasla.
You're just having intent about what you're thinking about the type of
the כלי. kli. Oh that looks like a nice frying pan or
something like that even though it's not it's not a frying pan
it's a baking pan. But okay but you're not identifying the nature
of the מנחה. Mincha מנחת מחבת לשם מנחת מרחשת במנחה דפסול במחשבה
קמחשב. Minchas machavas leshem minchas marcheshes bemincha depasul bemachshava kamachashev.
So for him the question is not that it's all one category
or that it's obviously false it's just you're not making a problem
because you're just talking about the vessel. So גמרא Gemara says והתנא
מפני שמעשיה מוכיחין עליה קאמר ve'atana mipnei shema'aseha mochichin aleha ka'amar but
but the reason given is because it's obviously false right? That's the
reason it's obviously false. גמרא says no הכי קאמר hacha ka'amar אף
על גב דמחשבה מינכר היא דפסיל af al gav demachshava minkar hi
d'pasel okay even though meaning like like the previous answer just because
it's obviously false and that's a reason to think that it should
be a problem it's not a problem because it's only at the
end of the day about the vessel not about the identity. ומה
אבל בזבחים אינו כן Umai aval bizvachim eino ken ah yeah I
know well that's what we're switching ומה אבל בזבחים אינו כן umai
aval bizvachim eino ken אף על גב דשחיטה אחת לכולם זריקה אחת
לכולם קבלה אחת לכולם בזבח דפסול במחשבה קמחשב. af al gav deshachita
achas lekulam zerika achas lekulam kabala achas lekulam bizvacha depasul bemachshava kamachashev.
Right again we're talking we're switching the reason to the אף על
גב. af al gav. Okay but by קרבנות korbanot even though the
act is not obviously the כוונה kavana is not obviously false this
approach thinks that if it's obviously false it's a bigger problem. So
by the מנחה Mincha although it's obviously false and should be a
bigger problem it's not a problem because you're only talking about the
vessel whereas by an animal sacrifice although it's not obviously false and
shouldn't be a big problem it's still no good because you're thinking
about the identity of the קרבן korban and you're thinking about the
שחיטה shechita and the identity of the קרבן. korban. Okay so basically
we bracket what seems to be the explanation for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon Again the only one that really worked with the simple read
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is רבא Rava because he said that
it's a question by whether it's obviously false or not obviously false.
These two reads are sort of saying even though. Okay and according
to this read which is really about so again רבא Rava's read
is if it's obviously false it's not a problem. רבא Rava's read
is all מנחות minchos are one fundamental category and therefore it's not
a problem if you stay within the מנחה Mincha category. And רב
אשי Rav Ashi's read is if you're thinking about vessels it's not
a problem if you're thinking about the identity of the קרבן korban.
it is. Okay so אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי
amar leh Rav Acha breih de-Rava le-Rav Ashi חריבה משום בלולה אמאי
charevah mishum belulah amai let's say it is a dry מנחה Mincha
and you're having intent that it is a wet one okay so
that's not about a vessel that's about the identity of the מנחה
Mincha you're thinking that this is a wet מנחה Mincha and it's
a dry one. Okay so
אמאי אמר רבי שמעון? amai amar Rabbi Shimon? אמר
ליה amar leh משום בילה בעלמא. mishum bilah be'alma. No when he's
thinking I'm doing this dry one for a wet he's not thinking
that I'm doing this for the sake of a moist מנחה. Mincha
He's saying I'm thinking about it doing this because of I don't
know what does רש"י Rashi say because I lest where where was
he?
Yeah it's just like I'm just I'm just having intent that I'm
just doing it for I don't know for like
you know it's I'm not even defining the מנחה Mincha. like I'm
just thinking about about how I'm going to have my porridge at
home. So when I'm taking this מנחה mincha, and I'm saying for
the sake of something wet since I don't say a wet מנחה
mincha, I just say for the sake of something wet it's like
I say I'm taking this מנחה mincha for the sake of porridge
okay which is again just a meaningless statement. Since it's not saying
a wet מנחה mincha I'm not identifying it the type of the
מנחה mincha I'm just saying for something wet right it's like saying
I'm I'm taking this מנחה for the sake of my wet towel.
Okay so it's a stupid statement but it's not an invalidating one
because it's not about the identity of the מנחה. So the גמרא
says, אי הכי לשום שלמים נמי. ei hachi lishum shelamim nami. So
why wouldn't you שחט a חטאת for the sake of a שלמים?
Shelamim Why don't we say it means that you're not doing it
for a קרבן שלמים, korban shelamim, you're doing it for the sake
of making peace? Okay, לשום שלמי בעלמא. lishum shalmi b'alma. So he
says הכי השתא, hachi hasha,
what type of comparison is that? התם זבח גופיה איקרי שלמים. hasam
zevach gufe ikri shelamim. שלמים is the name of the קרבן. korban,
דכתיב המקריב את דם השלמים הזורק את דם השלמים. deksiv hamakriv es
dam hashelamim hazorek es dam hashelamim. Okay, so
but when you say לשם בלוה lishain bilah or you know wet,
wet is not the name of the קרבן. korban. מנחה בלולה Minchas
belula is the name of a קרבן, korban. okay. הכא מנחה גופיה
מיקרי בלולה וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן כתיב. hacha mincha gufa mikre belula
vechol mincha belula bashemen kesiv.
It's an adjective describing מנחה, but it's not the name of the
מנחה, it's not a proper name. בלולה בשמן איקרי בלולה סתם לא
איקרי. bilula bashemen ikri bilula stam lo ikri. Okay, so basically what
we have is again it's a very technical like word game, okay,
but the bottom line is that you have in order to re-identify
it you have to give it the name of a different קרבן.
korban. So saying לשום מחבת lishum machavas is not the name of
a different קרבן. korban.
לשום בלולה lishum blula is not the name of a different קרבן.
korban. It's not the name of a כלי, cli, but it's not
the name of a different קרבן. korban? You would have to say
לשום מנחה בלולה. lishum mincha blula. So for him that's what invalidates
to explicitly give it the label of a different קרבן. korban, Okay,
כולהו כרבה לא אמרי, kulei k'rabba lo amri, they didn't say רבה's
Rabba explanation, which was the simplest read: is it obviously false or
not obviously false?
דאדרבה מחשבה דמינכרא פסר רחמנא, de'adraba machshava de'minkara pasar rachmana, because they're
assuming the more obviously false it is the more it should invalidate.
It shouldn't be better because it's obviously false, it should be worse
because it's obviously false. כרבא לא אמרי, k'rava lo amri, they didn't
say like רבא, Rava, who said that it's about מנחות minchos all
being in one category.
זאת תורת המנחה zos toras hamincha they don't buy זאת תורת המנחה
zos toras hamincha that we get to put all מנחות minchos fundamentally
in one category and you could also say that then logically also
you should say the same thing by a חטאת and maybe they're
not prepared to say the same thing by a חטאת. כרב אשי
לא אמרי, k'rav ashi lo amri, they didn't say like רב אשי
Rav Ashi that says that it's whether you name the מנחה or
whether you name an adjective or the vessel. משום קשיא דרב אחא
בריה דרבא mishum kashya d'rav acha brei d'rava because of the question
that we just asked of רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha brei
d'Rava which
was about what, which was about בלולה? blula? Oh yeah, חריבה משום
בלולה. chareiva mishum blula. Okay now מילתא דפשיטא ליה לרבה להאי גיסא
ולרבא להאי
גיסא מיבעיא ליה לרב הושעיא. milsa depishitei lei lerabba lahai gisa ul'rava
lahai gisa mibayei lei l'rav oshaya. This question about whether an obviously
invalid intent make it better or worse, that was the debate of
רבה Rabba and רבא, Rava, that was the question of רב הושעיא.
Rav Oshaya. דבעי רב הושעיא, debayei rav oshaya, רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya
asked, רמי ליה בעי מיניה רב הושעיא מרב אסי: rami lei baye
minei rav oshaya merav asi: מנחה לשום זבח מה מאי אמר רבי
שמעון? mincha lishum sevach mah mai amar rabbi shimon? If you do
a מנחה for the sake of an עולה what would he say?
If it's obviously wrong does that make
it
not a problem, which is רבה's Rabba read, the simple read, and
this is obviously wrong and therefore not a problem? או דילמא טעמא
דרבי שמעון משום דכתיב זאת תורת המנחה וזבח
לא כתיב, o dilma ta'ama d'rabbi shimon mishum dekesiv zos toras hamincha
vezevach lo kesiv, or is it because all מנחות are one category?
Okay, but a מנחה for the sake of an עולה would invalidate.
So meaning how do you read רבי שמעון? Do you read him
רבה's Rabba way or רבא's Rava way? Okay, אמר ליה כלום הגענו
סוף דעתו של רבי שמעון? amar lei kelumi ganu sof da'ato d'rabbi
shimon? Do you think we've figured out רבי שמעון? Like we don't
really know at the end of the day what the reason of
רבי שמעון is. There are different ways of reading him.
כרבה לא משני ליה, k'rabba lo mishani lei, he didn't just adopt
רבה's Rabba position משום קשיא דאביי mishum kashya d'abaye because what אביי
Abaye asked רבה. Rabba. Now that's a little different explanation. אביי Abaye
challenged רבה Rabba when רבה Rabba said if it's obviously wrong. He
said, "But wait a minute, רבי שמעון links, you know, says קדש
קדשים היא כחטאת וכאשם, kodesh kodashim hi k'chatas ukh'asham, so all bad
מחשבות machshavos should be the same the same way all bad מחשבות
machshavos are the same by קרבנות." korbanos. So that's a reason not
to adopt that approach because according to that approach you should equate
all bad
מחשבות. machshavos. כרבא לא משני ליה k'rava lo mishani lei משום קשיא
דזאת תורת החטאת. mishum kashya d'zos toras hachatas. He didn't want to
say רבא's Rava right because זאת תורת החטאת zos toras hachatas if
you're going to say all מנחות are the same you should say
all חטאות chataos are the same. כרב אשי לא משני ליה k'rav
ashi lo mishani lei משום קשיא דרב אחא בריה דרבא mishum kashya
d'rav acha brei d'rava and he didn't want
to adopt רב אשי Rav Ashi because then חריבה משום בלולה, chareiva
mishum blula, why is that not a problem? And he didn't like
that answer לשם בלוה בעלמא. lishain bilah b'alma. So basically we have
three different reads of רבי שמעון. רבה's Rabba read certainly fits the
words better but maybe has the most problems in terms of cases
that then logical consequence of what it should mean for other cases
and the גמרא has not concluded what רבי שמעון's reason is. Is
רבי שמעון's reason the more obviously false it is the less of
a problem it is, or do you say no, the more obviously
false it is the bigger of a problem it is and רבי
שמעון's reason is all מנחות are one category? Or is רבי שמעון's
issue a more technical point
that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo has to be give it the name
of a different קרבן? And חריבה chareiva and בלולה blula and מחבת
is not the name of a קרבן, you need to explicitly say
מנחה בלולה, mincha blula, מנחה חריבה, mincha chareiva, and otherwise it's a
meaningless intent. So we end with this.